Guide to the Oregon Department of Fish and Wildlife Records 1902-1981
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Oregon Department of Fish and Wildlife records
1902-1981
1960-1977
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Mss 2860
Oregon Department of Fish and Wildlife
.75 linear foot (2 document cases)
The Oregon Department of Fish and Wildlife enforces protective regulations for the conservation of Oregon's fish and wildlife. Records include documents relating to the Confederated Tribes of the Umatilla Indian Reservation lawsuits to protect traditional fishing and hunting practices, wild game laws and regulations, game management, and histories of regulations, game birds and the Oregon State Game Commission.
History of the Oregon Department of Fish and Wildlife:
The Oregon Department of Fish and Wildlife (ODFW) was originally established as the Oregon State Fish Commission in 1878. Initially, its duty was to enforce fishing regulations and the 1848 Territorial Constitution to ensure the conservation of salmon runs. Under the direction of Hollister McGuire in 1893, the agency's duties were expanded to include protection of wildlife from exploitative hunting. Since then, the ODFW has enforced protective regulations for the conservation of Oregon's fish and wildlife.
Records (1902-1981) include documents relating to the Confederated Tribes of the Umatilla Indian Reservation lawsuits to protect traditional fishing and hunting practices, Oregon's Cooperative Road Closure Program, and a roundtable discussion with department biologists.
Other materials include wild game laws and regulations, Oregon's program for management of marine mammals, game management, and histories of regulations, game birds and the Oregon State Game Commission.
The records contain correspondence which relates to Oregon Governor Tom McCall and the Confederated Tribes of the Umatilla Indian Reservation lawsuits.
The collection is arranged topically.
The collection is open to the public.
Gift of the Oregon Department of Fish and Wildlife, 1989 (Accession number 19904).
Materials will be added to this collection.
Oregon Department of Fish and Wildlife Photographs, Organized Lot 790, Oregon Historical Society Research Library.
The photographs contained in this collection range from the early 1890s to the early 1980s, allowing for an in depth look into the evolution of the ODFW. The primary subjects include fish and wildlife management activities, fishways, dams, hatcheries, and law enforcement.
William L. Finley Photographs, Organized Lot 369, Oregon Historical Society Research Library.
Images of wildlife, primarily birds of the western United States, circa 1900-1940s, photographed by William Lovell Finley and his associate Herman T. Bohlman, with the help of his wife, Nellie Irene Barnhart Finley, and others. The collection includes fine images of adult and immature birds, chicks, eggs, and nests. Many show habitat. Others document the camera equipment and techniques used to make the photographs.
Oregon Department of Fish and Wildlife records are available at the Oregon State Archives in Salem, Oregon.
The collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings:
Oregon. Dept. of Fish and Wildlife --Archives.
Wildlife management--Oregon.; Fishery management--Oregon.; Wildlife conservation--Oregon.; Fishery conservation--Oregon.; Game protection--Oregon.; Game laws--Oregon.; Fishery law and legislation--Oregon.; Umatilla Indians--Fishing.
Agriculture; Fisheries and Wildlife; Native Americans; Oregon
Letters.; Reports.; Legal documents.
- Survey of Agricultural Damage by Bird and Mammal Pests in Oregon, 1963-1970 (Box-folder 1/1)
- Umatilla Fish Case No. 64-317, 1965 (Box-folder 1/2)
  Transcripts of court proceedings
- Second Umatilla Game Case vs. Holcomb appeal file, 1965-1967 (Box-folder 1/3)
  Court documents and correspondence
- Umatilla Fish Case No. 77-59--court documents, 1968 (Box-folder 1/4)
- First Umatilla Civil Action No. 77-59, reopening Three Mile Dam site, 1960-1966 (Box-folder 1/5)
- Court documents, notes and news clippings
  - Civil Action No. 68-409, Richard Sohappy, et al vs. McKee A. Smith, et al--court documents, 1968 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Game Commissioners--photocopied images, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Game bird and big game seasons, 1969 (Box-folder 1/8)
    Statistics on species, hunters, hunter days and total kill
  - Correspondence relating to Oregon Governor Tom McCall, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Oregon's Program for the Management of Marine Mammals, 1973 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Oregon Department of Fish and Wildlife reorganization, 1975 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Oregon's Cooperative Road Closure Program, 1977 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - A Report to the 1977 Legislature on Court Disposition of Fish and Wildlife Law Violations, 1976 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Roundtable Discussion of Oregon Fish and Wildlife Commission Members with Department Wildlife Biologists, 1978 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Clerical/Secretarial Training Sessions, circa 1970 (Box-folder 1/15)
    Agenda and needs analysis questionnaire responses.
  - Executive Department--Governor, 1974-1975; 1980-1981 (Box-folder 1/16)
- Correspondence and reports
  - Shooting Preserve Laws and Regulations, circa 1969 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - History of Big Game Regulations (1899-1970), 1971 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Game license sales history, 1912-1979 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Brief History of Oregon's Game Birds, circa 1960 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Course material--history of the Oregon Game Commission, circa 1950 (Box-folder 1/21)
- Oregon history from 1792 with transparencies
  - History and Policies of the Oregon Game Commission, circa 1950 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Historical material, circa 1930-1972 (Box-folder 2/2)
    Histories of the Oregon State Game Commission, regulations, reports, statistics, lists of board members and game wardens, and logo.
  - News clipping, 1902 (Box-folder 2/3)
    Synopsis of Oregon's game and fish laws
  - Report of Gene M. Simpson, Superintendent of State Game Farms, 1931 (Box-folder 2/4)
    Report in bound volume on pheasants, quail and wild turkeys raised on state game farms, including photographs